This episode is brought to you by Accenture. When your advertising operations fall out of sync, everything else follows. Spotify and Accenture are working together to reinvent the rhythm of ad sales, using automation, analytics, and smarter workflows to simplify campaign delivery and access better data across the business. The result? Less time spent on operations, more time connecting brands with the moments and fandoms that matter most. Learn more at Accenture.com slash Spotify.
The new LinkedIn hiring pro can't undo your last hire. The human post-poner. They were the master of one phrase. I'll circle back on that. But three months later, you were the one doing all their work and wondering how big that circle is. But LinkedIn hiring pro can take the hiring load off your plate by automating the hiring busy work from the initial job post to scheduling interviews. Hire right the first time with LinkedIn hiring pro. Post a free job today at linkedin.com slash quality.
All right, welcome back for what to me at least feels like the first week of summer. The kids out of school. Nice to see you. Before I get into your questions today, which have been great, by the way, thank you for sending them. That's what's gonna make this show great. You can send them to pod at longtermwords.com. Keep them coming, that would be great. Before we get into that, I wanna talk about something that has bothered me for a long time. I've written about a little bit, spoken about a little bit, but I hear it almost every time I go out and do a presentation somewhere else, speak to a group of people.
and you do a Q&A. The single most question that I get and have been getting for 20 years, same question, some variation of the question, how do you make decisions in today's world that is so uncertain? And it's always framed as like, it used to be certain in the past, but today we have this uncertainty. It's always like that, that we live in an abnormal, uncertain time. And look, I won't discount that there's a lot of volatility.
craziness, insanity, bad behavior, poor decisions, all of that in the world. And as things, new technologies, AI, whatever it might be, there's all there's some there's plenty of things to look at today and say, look, given this craziness that we're dealing with and the uncertainty of the future, how do you make decisions? What I've always disagreed with and I understand why it gets framed like this, but I've always disagreed with is the idea that what we're living through today is more uncertain than it was at various points in the past.
at almost any point in the past. The past always seems more certain than it was to those living at the time, because we know how that story ends. It's always like that. There's a great quote that I love, which is, everything feels unprecedented when you haven't engaged with history. If I've said that quote a million times on the podcast before, I'll say it a million times more, because I think it's fantastic. And whenever people talk about how uncertain current times are, I always want to stop and say,
When were times certain or at least relatively more certain than they are today? When was there less uncertainty than there is today? And the point of periods in the past that I think you could easily quickly stop and say, no, no, no, no, that was an unbelievably uncertain time. And so people will point to, let's say the 1990s, particularly the late 1990s when there was relative to a lot of other times in history, a feeling at least of geopolitical stability, economic stability.
cultural stability at least relative to previous times and we'll say like those were the good days those were the glory days and party wants to say okay, so we're talking about the late 1990s as in you know 24 months before 9 11 completely upended everything that we know in the modern world economically politically culturally that was the certainty that was when we could see the future with a lot of foresight maybe 2006 2007 when we had finally recovered from that post 9 11
Stupor and fear that was the certainty just before the financial crisis That you probably didn't see coming and completely upended everything about the world that you know maybe 2012 2013 when we finally started getting over the financial crisis just before Whether it was Brexit or the political climate in the United States turned for whatever it is that we're in right now Maybe you feel that the world was common certain in 2018 2019 just before COVID came out of the middle of nowhere and
Upended every single aspect of your life whenever you look back at those periods with a sense of those were the good old days it inevitably like the irony is what you think was certainty as if what you the period that you thought you could see the future with the most amount of clarity is actually in hindsight the period just before Things were about to fall off the cliff. It's a period that in hindsight was the most uncertain That's always the irony of it a big part of this too. There's this great Russian quote that I love which is
talking about nostalgia, and it says, the past is more uncertain than the future, which is like how we remember the past is so up for interpretation and we miss remember what things actually felt like and were going on. And so when you know how the story ends in hindsight, you look back at the past and you think those were the good days because you can't remember how much you worried about the future, a future that you didn't know how it was going to pan out. But we do know how it panned out when we're looking back in hindsight.
And so at any given moment, it always feels like the present is more uncertain than the past. When I think the truth is without minimizing anything that's going on today, I don't think the world today is more uncertain than it was 10 years ago, 20 years ago, 30 years ago. I was reading a book recently called The Fourth Turning, pretty famous book. A lot of you have probably read it, mixed feelings about it, but it was an interesting book nonetheless. But that book written in the 1990s,
was talking about as kind of a passing point. This wasn't the main thrust of the book, but was talking about how at the present time that they were writing it in the 90s, the mood of the country was so bad. And people were negative and they were pessimistic. And then the political climate was not great relative to what it had been. And that was written in the 1990s. And then you fast forward today and we're like, those were the good old days.
And when it was, book was written in the 1990s, it was talking about how everyone in the 90s was yearning for the good old days in the 80s. And in the 80s, you go back to then, and they were yearning for the good old days of the 60s. Nobody yearned for the 70s, the 70s were terrible. But that's, I think that's generally how it works. It's always once you know how the story ends, the past looks so great, and the present that you're living in feels so fearful. And that actually, I think is actually pretty optimistic that it...
It's painful to wake up and think that you are now living in the age of uncertainty when the reality is everyone always has always. Everyone at every point in time is staring down a future that could go in many different directions, big risks that nobody sees coming. That's true today. It's absolutely true today. And it's always been true. All right, one last thing before I get into your questions. Just a quick little snippet kind of out of the middle of nowhere here. I wrote about an MIT scientist.
in the psychology of money in Robert Weinberg. And Robert Weinberg is a molecular biologist who studies cancer, which is something that I know absolutely nothing about. But what I've loved about Robert Weinberg is that he's very well spoken. He can just explain things in a way that if you're not a PhD molecular biologist, you can understand. And so he's been in several documentaries and he's done several interviews that I've always thought I'm just a really smart and articulate guy. And he did an interview many years ago and I was watching it on YouTube recently.
I'd read about this before, I was watching it, and I just thought he just made such a astute, articulate point. And the point was about the fact that he has worked at MIT for 50 years. He did his undergraduate degree there, and he's still working there 50 years later. And about how much benefit that gave to his career that he had been in one spot in one office for half a century. I just want to play this little snippet for you. Here's what he said. People say to me sometimes, how could you stay at one place for so long?
We all know the lives of academic gypsies who spend three years here, 14 years there, five years there. And each time, each place they settle down, they make friends, social friends, colleagues. And then after a period of time, they and their families are uprooted and moved to some other place. And there's never any constancy in their lives, never any robust social network, never any lifelong friends who one can associate with.
And so I have no regret having been a stick in the mud, having never really moved very far, and working now only a couple hundred yards from where I was an undergraduate in the dorm at MIT. I think that applies to so many aspects of life, no matter what you do or where you work or what you're doing. The value of sticking with something through thin and thick and thin and letting the benefits of social compounding accrue to you
Maybe that's the important point. People know financial compounding. They know like earning interest on interest. They know how that money compounds over time. It's harder to contextualize social compounding of the value of friendships and trust, the value of understanding how an organization works, understanding people's different personalities, compounding memories that become your most valuable asset over time. Look, this is not to say you should always stick with every relationship and job and whatever it might be.
even if it's not obviously not working out. That's not the point. But it's easy to discount the value of sticking with something for a very long period of time. My wife sent me this Instagram video this past week. It went viral. I'm sure some of you have seen it. It's this older gentleman who is packing up from his house. His house is completely empty. Like he's just moved out and he's in this empty living room and he calls out the name of his children who are not there. So he's sitting in this empty living room and he goes, Jack.
Caroline and it's like echoing throughout this empty house. And this is, you realize that this is his last moment in this house that he's lived in for a very long time. And then he walks out and he locks the door and that's the end of the existence. And it's a very powerful video of just, you think about the memories that took place in there and whatnot. And I always think about that, that as Charlie Munger says, the first rule of compounding is to never interrupt it unnecessarily. And memories compound, relationships compound, the value of sticking with something for a very long time.
whether it's a relationship or a career or a job, whatever it might be, is profound. So thank you, Robert Weinberg. All right, let me get into your questions. And thank you again for your questions. Standard reminder, I'm not your financial advisor. Speak to a real one if you actually want personalized advice. This question is from Brian. And Brian asks, how far is too far when it comes to making investment decisions that appear to make it easier to stick with an investing strategy? With the rise of both ESG,
and faith-based investments over the last few years, what would you say to someone who sees these investments and wants to invest in accord with their values? And so these are the important two questions that he asks. Brian, the answer to those last two questions, which I'll just summarize again,
Is it helpful for an investor to invest in what may look like a quirky strategy if it helps you stick with it or are there's quirky strategies just trendy? The answer to both those questions is yes. We start with the first question. Are these things ESG, Faith, Best Investments, whatever it is, quirky? I wouldn't use the word fad necessarily, although some of them might actually be that. But I just have this view that there are two ways to invest. One is passive.
where you're just owning a broad diversified index fund and you don't really know any of the individual companies in there. You're owning a slice of the economy and you leave it alone or hardcore active. You are like devoting your life to truly understanding every single bit and aspect of this investment. It's not for the weak. There's only a small number, small percentage of people who should be doing anything like that. And even of those who do it, an even smaller percentage will actually succeed doing it. And so what exists in between
kind of like the quasi-active, I think can get kind of dangerous. Because you're basically saying, look, by just tweaking one little tiny lever here of, oh, I'm only gonna own this subset of companies, I'm not gonna own this subset of companies, that's gonna lead to better performance over time. That kind of one foot in, one foot out style of investing, I think can be dangerous. It gives the appeal that you're using your IQ and intelligence to earn superior investing returns over time.
I don't know whether the evidence actually stacks up to show that it necessarily does. Your second question of whether you should be doing something like that because it helps you stick with it is very important and this is why I want to answer your question. A subpar investing strategy that you can stick with is always going to do better and perform better than a quote unquote perfecting investing strategy that you're going to get scared out of or bored of or give up over time.
If you view the advice of like, do what you love as a guide to a happier life, it sounds like a fortune cookie, right? That's kind of like empty advice. But if you view do what you love and do what feels good as the thing that provides endurance for your strategy, it makes it more likely for you to stick with a strategy over time because you enjoy it and you feel good about it and it aligns with your values and whatnot. If that gives you the endurance to stick with it through thick and thin, amazing, you should do it.
Even if, as I said in the first answer, it might be a quirky, maybe even fattish investing strategy. One very well-known example of this in investing that's been very well documented is what's called the home bias in investing, which basically shows that American investors only own US stocks, German investors only own German stocks, Japanese investors only own Japanese stocks. More or less, that tends to be true. There's not a lot of international diversification within investors around the world.
That is not rational. It's not rational to think the best companies that I should own are the ones that are located closest to my house. That doesn't make any sense, but it's actually very reasonable if owning companies that you're familiar with increases the odds that you can stick with those investments over time. And so if you take an investor in the United States and you say, which of these two companies is a better investment? Walmart or an oil refinery in Kazakhstan?
Actually, no, no, it's possible that the oil refinery and Cosic Stand is gonna perform very well over time. I don't know, make it all this up. But if you were to give that to a US investor and say, which of these two companies are you likely to stick with over the next 20 years? Overwhelmingly, it would be Walmart because you know them. You drive past it, maybe you shop there, you see the advertisements, you're very familiar that this is a real company, you understand the product, you understand the service, you're more likely to stick with it. Is that fattish to only invest in the companies in the country that you live in?
Maybe, yeah. Does it make sense from a spreadsheet academic finance perspective? Absolutely not. Is it the right thing to do in these situations? Very often times, the answer is yes. If you enjoy an investing strategy and it fits with your values and that is going to increase the odds of sticking with it, almost nothing else matters over time. Almost nothing matters more in investing than the odds that you can stick with an investing strategy during the lean years.
When things are not working in your favor, when the returns are not that good, if you can merely not give up during those trying moments, nothing else matters more in investing. There was this theory by PIMCO, the big bond fund company that I read about many years ago and they called it strategic mediocrity. What they meant by that was PIMCO was in any given year was gonna look pretty mediocre relative to their peers.
But a lot of their peers were going to get washed out or give up or get bored or whatever it might be, whereas PIMCO is just going to keep shrugging along year after year after year after year. And so over a course of 10 or 20 years, it would beat the vast majority of its peers, even if in any given year it was boring. It could stick with it. And the value that it was going to provide over time was time. Time was the genius that was giving all the returns. And so whatever you do in your investing psychology,
to increase your endurance. Even if you know it's a suboptimal investing strategy, is the right thing to do. I'll give you one other example of this from personal finance that's been written about a lot. Everyone knows Dave Ramsey, the guy who kind of sits and answers questions about people's personal finances. I think he's a good guy. And he had this concept that he's come up with, came famous for it called the debt snowball, which is if you have a bunch of credit cards with a lot of credit card debt on it and you want to pay them off, don't start with the highest interest rate, paying off the highest interest rate.
That would be the rational thing to do, but psychologically what you want to do is pay off the card that has the lowest balance. Not the highest interest rate, the lowest balance. Because once you extinguish the debt from that card, it feels like you're making progress and then you're jazzed and you're excited to keep going. You have a lot of motivation. That is another example of it doesn't make statistical sense. You can't explain it in Excel. And in fact, statistically, mathematically,
It's not the right thing to do. And psychologically, it's the best thing to do, and that's why it works. All right, question from Jason.
and technology and innovation. Because to your point, the too good to be true aspect of it does tend to play out in the short term when something first comes out, when there is a new breakthrough that promises to completely change the world. Maybe it's not necessarily too good to be true, but it takes much longer for society to adopt it than you might think. My favorite example of this by far, a little story, is in 1955, when Ford Motor,
came and started selling for the first time in automobiles a new profound invention called the seatbelt. It was a new thing at the time. Most people before then just threw themselves and their children in the back of the car and best of luck, hold on tight if we get in an accident. Ford started selling seatbelts and it was cheap. It was like $17 when you buy a car to add on a seatbelt as a new attachment.
The data that we had at the time showed that they reduced traffic fatalities by like 90%. This was unbelievable, this new simple invention called a seatbelt that's going to, and auto fatalities were so high back then. And now we have this like very simple thing to reduce fatalities by so much. And what happened after that? And the answer is 2% of Ford customers opted for a seatbelt. 98%
afford customers who knew the data of how much they were going to reduce traffic fatalities, chose to remain at the mercy of inertia when they drove a car. It took four or five decades before seatbelts were like a universal thing. And it wasn't even because people wanted them necessarily, it was because they became the law. And so there are examples over time when you have a new breakthrough, if you want to see, think of a seatbelt like that, that promises to profoundly make people more healthy.
And most people in society look at it and say, no, thank you. And you see it all over the history of science. I recorded this passage from Nassim Talib's book, Anti-Fragile, where he says, quote,
The difference between discovering, inventing a new profound breakthrough and that having broad cultural acceptance can be not months or years, but decades or even centuries. I think that is where the too good to be true aspect comes in with new inventions. Whether GLP-1s have that same impact, we can see. And I think for most new inventions, a lot of the reason that this takes place, why there is such a profound gap between the new technology
that can make your life much better and widespread cultural adoption of that technology. I think there are a couple reasons for this. The first is that convincing people that you can solve their problems is actually harder than it seems because people don't want to be told that what they were doing before was wrong. And so if you had been driving in a car for decades already and then maybe you lost friends and family from car accidents and then Ford comes along and says, we have this new invention that's going to make everything safer.
The knee-jerk reaction, by and large, is not to say, great, thank you, I can't wait to start wearing that. It's almost this bad feeling that you've realized you've been doing it wrong all along. And you don't want to accept that for yourself. And so a lot of times the reaction to those new technologies is to actually push back on it. This is also true for when computers start coming about. And what do people say? It's not necessarily in the early days we have this new technology that makes communication so much easier.
what people actually do is they lament the decline of writing letters by hand. They don't want to be told or accept that the next generation is going to have a much easier time or safer time doing it than you did. And oftentimes, how that comes about and how that displays itself in society is pushing back against new technology.
And I'm not a healthcare expert in the slightest, so I can't answer your question directly with any expertise. But I would say I listened to a podcast this week from Derek Thompson. This podcast is called Plain English. It's fantastic. And it was about some of the new medical breakthroughs, whether it is in heart disease or cancer. In the last month, there have been some headlines that will make you turn your heads about new developments, new discoveries that could have profound impacts on heart disease and cancer. And Derek had a guest on the show who is a medical expert talking about this.
One of the answers, one of the drugs that they were talking about is a study from a new drug that is a kind of a one-and-done drug to lower cholesterol. And it's a gene-altering drug. I'm not an expert on this stuff in the slightest. But the point that this excerpt brought up that I thought was really good was, even if this does work and it's perfect, and there is a one-and-done shot to lower cholesterol for nearly everyone, is society ready to take that and say, take the shot to alter your genes?
Are people ready for that? That's a completely different topic. And I think the history of that would be no. And so at the broad philosophical point, the profound gap between new innovations and those innovations having a profound impact on society can be enormous. You saw that with the airplane. When the time between the Wright brothers building the airplane and people just accepting it that this was going to be a big new technology was years and years and years.
It's true for virtually every new technology. And it's a reminder of something we've talked a lot about before on the show, which is that good news almost always happens slow. Bad news usually happens very fast. It's overnight. It's a terrorist attack, a war, a pandemic that comes out and you can't ignore it. The world is fundamentally different in one night. Good news is usually the opposite. It happens very slow over time. And over time, it's profound.
But there's very rarely a time when you open up the newspaper and you say, hey, see, because of what happened today, the world is now much better, much safer, much healthier. All right, next question. This comes from Sir Minder, who asks, I'm interested in your opinion on what the easiest and most laid back way to build wealth is for the everyday person. Many people choose to invest in their own home.
and maybe even a rental property on the side, while others prefer to rent and invest solely in a broadly diversified stock market. Looking at historical returns and especially future trends, which path do you think is better for the average investor looking for peace of mind? Okay, I like this question because a lot of times when people talk about building wealth over time, it's usually displayed as two different options, which are stocks or real estate. Here's my thought about real estate.
I own a house. I love owning a house. I love being a homeowner. It is a very important part of my life and my psychology, my feeling of stability and whatnot. Never in a million years would I ever consider it an investment. A financial investment. It's a place where I raise my family in a neighborhood that I enjoy, in a house that I like, and I actually enjoy my life and I enjoy taking care of it and all that things, all that stuff. Even if the value of the house goes up over time. And I suspect it will. Once you factor in,
all of the costs of home ownership, whether it is insurance or property taxes or upkeep. And if you've never owned a house, wait until upkeep. It's one of the most agonizing things you can deal with. You realize that every house is maybe a beautiful house, but it's actually just a rotting pile of lumber and bricks at the end of the day. I never consider it a financial investment. A lot of this is because this is very simple math that confuses a lot of people with real estate. You just use a round number to make the math simple. If you buy a house for a million dollars,
and 20 years later you sell it for $2 million. How much money did you make? And the answer is not a million dollars because if you sell that house for $2 million, you probably have to use that money to buy another house to live in. And that other house that you live in also doubled in value over the same period of time. And so by and large, you did not earn necessarily anything because when you sell one house, you probably have to use that money to go buy another house that is in the same price environment, same price dynamic.
Now, you mentioned investing in rentals, and this is very different too. And a lot of people, when they talk about real estate investing, consider it quote-unquote passive investing. I'm going to own a bunch of rentals, and they're going to spit off rental income for me, and that's passive investing. Nobody who has actually ever owned residential real estate as rental properties considers it passive. For the same reason that owning your own house is just a rotting pile of lumber and bricks that needs constant upkeep.
an investment just to keep it going, the rental properties are the same. And not only are you dealing with properties that are breaking down, you're dealing with people who are gonna not pay their rent and complain and be loud neighbors and whatever it might be. Owning real estate as an investment, I think is the least passive form of income that you can possibly make. And so look, the people who do it well and do it right and devote their lives to managing it can do very well over time. And yes, there's...
property managers you can give, but it's going to eat into your returns and whatnot, and still you can deal with a lot of hassle here and there. In my view, owning a broad-based index fund of stocks is the least day-to-day investment required to building wealth over time.
There's a lot of psychological investment that's going to go into this of dealing with volatility and uncertainty. You have to deal with that. So nothing is necessarily passive. It's not psychologically passive. But in terms of the actual upkeep of what you need to give into it day to day, I think for most people, it tends to be one of the easiest ways to build wealth over a long period of time. And by the way, the stat now in America is like 60% of Americans own stocks in one form or another, even if it's just in their 401k, their retirement account.
And so not only is it the easiest way, but I think most people have caught onto that at this point, that it's a pretty easy way. I also think we don't talk enough about how fortunate we are to live in that era where it was not that long ago, 30, 40, 50 years ago, that that idea that an ordinary everyday person could invest in a very cheap, low-cost portfolio of stocks and own it over time.
was mythical. Like it was not like that at all. You by and large had to be a wealthier person who went to a stockbroker and paid the stockbroker an egregious fee to invest in stocks over time. And so the fact that that opportunity for ordinary people exists is a pretty wonderful thing. All right, before we go, one recommendation for you. I like documentaries. I love watching documentaries. Sometimes I think I like watching them more than books because there's music and sound and whatnot that gives a big emotional impact.
The best documentary I have ever seen in my life and it is not close is a documentary called New York a documentary film It was done by Rick Burns who is Ken Burns brother. I don't know what was in the water in that family, but they're just unbelievably good film makers. It's about the history of New York City From starting about the 1400s through today. It's 17 hours long
So brace yourself when you watch into this. But not only is it just a profound history of New York, which has had just sort of cultural impact and the history of immigration and whatnot, it's profound from a technical historical level. What is so good about it though, what is so unique about this documentary though, is the art of it. And you realize like how good and how important and how powerful the music is, the images are.
I've watched it. I can't count how many times I've watched this, at least different episodes of it. It's like an emotional experience watching this documentary. And so much of it, again, is the music that was just so perfectly matched with the scenes. And so not only do I recommend that documentary, I would challenge you as I've thought a lot about the power of storytelling. If you watch that documentary and you merely take out the background music, the value of it would fall like 90%.
I think about that a lot when it's like people don't want just good information. They want a good story. That's what moves the needle the most in the world. And so I'd encourage you to watch that documentary. If you have a spare 17 hours lying around to learn about the history of New York. That's it for this week. Thanks again for listening. We'll see you next time.
That's nice. Go on, book it. It's easy. Booking.com, Booking. Yeah. NFL football season is here, which means when you switch to Verizon, it feels like... Touchdown! Because you get NFL Sunday ticket from YouTube on us, when you buy an eligible 5G phone on select unlimited plans, which means you can watch every out-of-market game every Sunday afternoon. And it's all on us!
Now that's the Verizon way to kick off the NFL football season, right? Switch and get NFL Sunday ticket from YouTube on us, only with Verizon.